A Guide to the papers of James Major Colson IV 1882,1959
Johnston Memorial Library, Virginia State University
Special Collections and Archives, Johnston Memorial Library, Virginia State University
A Guide to the Papers of James Major Colson IV
Special Collections and Archives, Johnston Memorial Library, Virginia State University
1988-13b
65 items
Correspondence, financial, printed and other memorabilia of the Colson-Hill family. Acc. #1988-13b
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
A gift of James Major Colson IV
Biographical/Historical Information
James Major Colson IV was born in Petersburg Va. Mr.Colson was one of five children born to James M. and Kate Hill Colson. He graduated from the John A. Dix School in Dinwiddie County. He received his A.B. degree from Virginia Union University and a M.A. degree from New York University School of Business Administration.
During Mr.Colson's life he worked as a carpenter. He also worked for the New York City Bureau of Public Assistance, and the computer center at Virginia State University. He was married to Ernestine Winters and had one son by a previous marriage to Kate Gilpin Colson.
Scope and Content
The materials, which make up the James Major Colson Papers are clearly items removed from the Colson-Hill Family papers. These items include correspondence, scrapbooks, and a number of photographs. An inventory of these materials is available.
Series Descriptions
Series I. Records Book a meteorological record of Dinwiddie County covering the time 1901-1909..
Series II. Writings. Two short histories of the V.N. and C.I.
Series III. Photographs. Photographs of people and places. The Photographs appear to have been taken from Edna Meade Colson's papers.
Series IV. Printed. Invitations, programs, and other printed items collected by James Major Colson IV. An Interesting invitation concerning an Underground Railroad activity.
Series V. Artifacts. Objects colleted by Mr. James Major Colson, which include items from is grandfather John Henry Hill.
Contents List
- Ledger
  - Cooperative Observer's Meteorological Record, Dinwiddie 1901-1909
- Writings
  - History of V.N. and C.I. (Box-folder 1:1)
  - History of V.N. and C.I. (Box-folder 1:2)
- Photographs
  - Personals (Alphabetical Order)
    - Alexander, Blanche (Box-folder 1:3)
    - Bradley, Sarah (Box-folder 1:4)
    - Colson, E. (Box-folder 1:5)
    - Edna Colson and Anna Laura Lindsay (Box-folder 1:6)
    - James Major Colson IV (Box-folder 1:7)
    - William Nelson Colson (student teaching) (Box-folder 1:8)
    - William Nelson Colson (Hampton 1907-08) (Box-folder 1:9)
    - Hamilton, Cora (Box-folder 1:10)
    - Kate Hill (Box-folder 1:11)
    - Lawing, Ivy (Box-folder 1:12)
    - Walker, B. (Box-folder 1:13)
    - Whitley, Pearl (Box-folder 1:14)
  - Group Pictures and Singles
    - Virginia Union University Men (Box-folder 1:15)
    - Harmonia Club '06 Females (Box-folder 1:16)
    - Fisk Students men and women (Box-folder 1:17)
    - Fisk Students men and women (Box-folder 1:18)
    - Fisk women (Box-folder 1:19)
    - Fisk students men and women (Box-folder 1:20)
    - Fisk Students women (Box-folder 1:21)
    - Fisk women (Box-folder 1:22)
    - Fisk student female (Box-folder 1:23)
    - Fisk student female (Box-folder 1:24)
    - fisk student female (Box-folder 1:25)
    - Fisk student female (Box-folder 1:26)
    - Fisk student female (Box-folder 1:27)
    - Fisk student male (Box-folder 1:28)
    - Fisk student male (Box-folder 1:29)
    - Fisk student male (Box-folder 1:30)
    - Fisk student females (Box-folder 1:31)
    - Fisk Faculty (Box-folder 1:32)
  - Unidentified male and female Photographs
    - Unidentified females (Box-folder 1:33-39)
    - Unidentified males (Box-folder 1:40-48)
    - Unidentified males and females (Box-folder 49)
  - Unidentified children and couple
    - Unidentfied children (Box-folder 1:50-53)
    - Unidentified couple (Box-folder 1:54)
  - Undentified Buildings
    - Building at Fisk (Box-folder 1:55)
    - Teacher's College Building (Box-folder 1:56)
    - Unidentified Rooms at Dartmouth (Box-folder 1:57)
    - Unidentified Building (Box-folder 1:58)
  - Photo Album
    - scrap book, of Miss Amazda Meredith (Box-folder 1:59)
- Printed
  - Invitation Jubilee of Freedom N.D.- (Box-folder 2:1)
  - Invitation-weddings (Box-folder 2:2)
  - Invitation- Alpha Delta Phi (Box-folder 2:3)
  - Invintation- Class Day Dartmouth (Box-folder 2:4)
  - Invitation- Booker T Washingtton (Box-folder 2:5)
  - Invitation-Hampton - Negro Congference 1907 (Box-folder 2:6)
  - Invitation- V.N.I.I. (Box-folder 2:7)
  - Invitation- V.N.I.I. 1925 (Box-folder 2:8)
  - Invitation- Men's Dormitories- Open House 1949 (Box-folder 2:9)
  - Programs- Musical Program Bethel A.M.E. Church 1915 (Box-folder 2:10)
  - Delaware State Colored Teachers's Association 1927 (Box-folder 2:11)
  - Program- Commencement Exerciscs, Luthor P. Jackson High School 1953 (Box-folder 2:12)
  - Founders and Jackson Day Dinner 1959 (Box-folder 2:13)
  - Brochure-VA. Building and Savings Association 1882 (Box-folder 2:14)
  - Brochure- People's Building and Loan Association 1889 (Box-folder 2:15)
  - Flyer- The Weaver Home Bulletin 1925 (Box-folder 2:16)
  - Flyer- The Amster News N.D. (Box-folder 2:17)
  - Certificate- Scholarship Kate (Hill) Colson 1874-1875 (Box-folder 2:18)
  - Certificate- Golden Report- Peabody Edna Colson 1902 (Box-folder 2:19)
  - Certificate- Report Cards H. Colson Jackson 1915-1920 (Box-folder 2:20)
  - Certificate- Awarded to Ernestine Colson Central State Hospital 1975 (Box-folder 2:21)
  - Newsletter- First Anniversary of the Redwood USO Club 1943 (Box-folder 2:22)
  - Newsletter- Dunbar News Flashes Vol. 13 #2 1949 (Box-folder 2:23)
- Artifacts
  - Carpenter's Tools (Box 4)
  - World War I Officers Binoculars (Box 4)